<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Funerall elegies vpon the most lamentable and vntimely death of the thrice illustrious Prince Henry, Prince of VVales, &amp;c. By R.A.</title>
            <author>Allyne, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16948</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104377</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840115</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840115</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4587</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16948)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4587)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 818:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Funerall elegies vpon the most lamentable and vntimely death of the thrice illustrious Prince Henry, Prince of VVales, &amp;c. By R.A.</title>
                  <author>Allyne, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] P[urfoot] for Iohn Budge, and are to be sold at his shop at Brittaines Burse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. 1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Robert Allyne.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4587:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4587:1"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sir <hi>Thomas Erſkene</hi> Knight, Gentleman of the late Princes privie Chamber. <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hoſe timeleſſe teares on his vntimely fall,</l>
               <l>Who, in his time, bred ſolace to vs all,</l>
               <l>If ought, that's worth the reading, therein be,</l>
               <l>Duetie ſhould bid me dedicate to thee.</l>
               <l>But ſince there's nought but ſighes, and teares, and grones,</l>
               <l>Nor halfe ſo much of thoſe as fits our moanes.</l>
               <l>And yet ſuch as they are, I doe not ſee,</l>
               <l>To whome they rather do belong then thee,</l>
               <l>Then thee; whoſe intreſt in his life was moſt,</l>
               <l>And hath by death ſo deare a Maſter loſt,</l>
               <l>As time's vnable to produce his Peere,</l>
               <l>Nor euer did, nor euer ſhall I feare.</l>
               <l>For whome I ſigh'd out thoſe diſorder'd grones,</l>
               <l>For Mourners keepe no methode in their mones,</l>
               <l>But as the paſſion is conceau'd in thought</l>
               <l>Abruptly, ſo into the world'tis brought.</l>
               <l>Mourning's a naturall motion in the heart,</l>
               <l>And ſcornes to be reform'd by rules of Art.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4587:2"/>
               <l>Then (worthy Knight) ſuch as they are, receaue them,</l>
               <l>For were they better, none but thou ſhould haue them,</l>
               <l>And when my mourning muſe ſhall change anew,</l>
               <l>This ſable habite in a brighter hew,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I'le vrge my vtmoſt vaine, to bring to light</l>
               <l>Some worke more worthy of your Worſhips ſight.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips aſſured to command, ROBERT ALLYNE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:4587:2"/>
            <head>FVNERALL ELEGIES vpon the moſt lamentable death of the thrice illustrious Prince <hi>Henrie,</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Bbe channels roare, deepe ſtreames in ſilence runne:</l>
               <l>Small woes haue words, but mightie cares be mute.</l>
               <l>Speach can expreſſe ſome ſhallow mourners mone,</l>
               <l>But dare not vndertake deepe forrows fute,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Onelie ſalt teares, and windie ſighs diſcloſe</l>
               <l>Some airie vapours of our warrie woes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Immortall ſprings of in-exhauſted teares,</l>
               <l>Shall haue their moyſture firſt exhauſted drie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eolian</hi> winds which from darke caues appeares</l>
               <l>Shall ſigh out all their ſubſtance in the skie,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Before they can lament his loſſe too much,</l>
               <l>Who dying left not earth another ſuch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What cannot eloquence by ſweet detection</l>
               <l>Make moſt profoundly in our ſences ſinke,</l>
               <l>Having attainde ſuch exquiſite perfection,</l>
               <l>As to expreſſe more then the heart can thinke:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet neither tong, nor mind can ſpeake, nor meane,</l>
               <l>The halfe of halfe the loſſe which we ſuſtaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why ſhould deepe cares be skanted thus in ſpeach,</l>
               <l>Why ſhould not worlds of words attend our woes,</l>
               <l>Which might to th'earths remoteſt borders ſtretch,</l>
               <l>To pierce the flintie breaſts of proudeſt foes,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whence floods of teares might guſh to mourne his fall,</l>
               <l>Whoſe deare example doth concerne vs all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who while his Father rulde this mighty land</l>
               <l>With heavenly wiſedome is our Supreame head,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4587:3"/>
               <l>He might haue beene vnto that head a hand,</l>
               <l>His forces through another world to lead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe glorious conqueſts in the continent,</l>
               <l>The glory of our Iland might augment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While his victorious Father heere at home,</l>
               <l>Rulde his proceedings by diuine directions,</l>
               <l>Till both made famous by the fall of Rome,</l>
               <l>Had been admired for the earthes perfections.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah then could death haue never com'd too ſoone,</l>
               <l>Nor halfe thoſe teare: beene ſpent vppon his toombe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But in the golden morning of his age,</l>
               <l>To be bereft by death before his time;</l>
               <l>Whom nature had but ſhowne as on a ſtage,</l>
               <l>To be ſo much admired in his prime:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Leaſt if hee had attain'd to further fame,</l>
               <l>The worldes foure Monarchies had loſt their name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That wee by building vp our hopes too hie,</l>
               <l>Might, bejng fruſtrate, catch the deeper fall,</l>
               <l>Whome nature now beginning to envy,</l>
               <l>Would turne our painted joyes to bitter gall;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Permitting that braue Prince t'approch no nearer,</l>
               <l>That after death his loſſe might bee the dearer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Blind, touchles, taſteles, deafe, and ſenceles ſnake,</l>
               <l>Where were thy eyes, thy eares, thy ſences gone:</l>
               <l>O tis too true, when thou thoſe wounds did make,</l>
               <l>Nor eyes, nor eares, nor ſences thou hadſt none.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For if thou hadſt, (ah cruelleſt of vipers)</l>
               <l>His fall had ne're bred ſuch a world of weepers.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hadſt thou but ſeeene how braue he rulde his ſtead.</l>
               <l>With what a whirle-wind hee did ſhake his ſpeare,</l>
               <l>With what a Princely grace hee bare his head,</l>
               <l>What Majeſtie did in his lookes appeare,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The leaſt of thoſe, if thou hadſt eyes to ſee,</l>
               <l>Had throwne the forceles dart from trembling thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hadſt thou (vngentle elfe) had eares to heare him,</l>
               <l>In modeſt manly ſpeach his mind diſcloſe;</l>
               <l>Thy fatall dart had ne're had force to deare him,</l>
               <l>Or if ſmell, touch, or taſt, or all of thoſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:4587:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Or any of them all, could thee withſtand</l>
               <l>Thy ſteele had ſure falne harmeles from thy hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Either thou mean'ſt to throw all mortalls downe.</l>
               <l>To emptie th'earth beginning at the beſt.</l>
               <l>Or elſe all deadly hate in one to crowne,</l>
               <l>And neuer after to annoy the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or is there one that rules aboue thy head,</l>
               <l>Who with a thought can ſtrike a mortall dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O ſure there is, hee for our greevous ſinnes</l>
               <l>Bereft our deereſt hope, and for our ſake,</l>
               <l>God at his owne houſe judgement oft beginnes,</l>
               <l>The head bejng hurt, to make the members quake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whome to containe this Ile was all too ſtraight;</l>
               <l>Him heavens thought worthy of a higher ſeat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of whome may well be ſaid as in the ſtorie,</l>
               <l>Was ſayd by <hi>Phillip</hi> many yeeres before,</l>
               <l>Of his braue Child, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>And true it proou'd; but we may ſay't much more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not <hi>Macedone,</hi> nor <hi>Brittaine,</hi> but the earth</l>
               <l>Was all too baſe to hold ſo great a birth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Go death, and mount in victories amaine,</l>
               <l>Diſperſe thy conqueſts in a wofull volume,</l>
               <l>Amongſt th'inſulting ſonnes of <hi>Ottomaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How Chriſtendome hath loſt her chiefeſt colume.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Haplie thoſe <hi>Paynimes</hi> ſhall applaud the ſame,</l>
               <l>And raiſe eternall trophies of thy ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Go dull the eares of Antichriſtian Rome,</l>
               <l>With ſweeter muſicke then the earth can yeild;</l>
               <l>Whoſe Bow'ls did late within her breſt conſume,</l>
               <l>To ſee great <hi>Brittaines</hi> heyre to braue the field</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Againſt proud <hi>Babell,</hi> and her champion <hi>Spaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>T'haue brought the Goſpell in requeſt againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell thou haſt brought to his vntimely toombe,</l>
               <l>One who in time had com'de t'haue worne the crowne</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Brittaine,</hi> and throwne downe the walles of Rome,</l>
               <l>And layd them leuell with the loweſt ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And all that envi'de at great <hi>Brittaines</hi> blis,</l>
               <l>Shall change their mourning, and rejoyce at this.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:4587:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But <hi>Brittaine</hi> ſhall conſume her ſelfe in teares,</l>
               <l>And bath her wofull face in floods of brine,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of dayes, nor monthes, nor yeares</l>
               <l>Confine her griefe, vntill by grace diuine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our young ſucceeding Prince expreſſe in time</l>
               <l>The high worth which the world expect'd of him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ô (God graunt) he may performe no leſſe,</l>
               <l>Nay rather may ſo farre exceed his brother,</l>
               <l>As he in higheſt gifts of hopefulneſſe,</l>
               <l>And Princely vertues did ſurpaſſe all other.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That once great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> and the world may vtter,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Henrie</hi> dy'de but to admit his better.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And truely if the eye, and brow, and face,</l>
               <l>Do not deceiue the ſence with falſe conceites,</l>
               <l>Which beare I know not what Maieſtike grace;</l>
               <l>But greater farre then ſhines in lower ſtates.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How farre the Lyons lookes exceedes the Lambes,</l>
               <l>So farre thy ſhow braue Prince excelles a mans.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If theſe deceiue not, as indeed they do not,</l>
               <l>Theſe rules of <hi>Phiſnom'e</hi> cannot wrong informe.</l>
               <l>What though thy yeres do promiſe what they owe not;</l>
               <l>Yet more then they haue promiſ'd they'le performe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And (ô would God) I might but liue to ſee,</l>
               <l>That hope effect'd, which all conceiue of thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That yet our Barbarous en'mies in the Eaſt,</l>
               <l>Within the Empire of old <hi>Babilon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And that proud miſticke <hi>Babell</hi> in the Weaſt,</l>
               <l>That holdes the cup of fornication,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By whoſe vile dregs the Kings on earth are drunke,</l>
               <l>May be in deepe of darke confuſion ſunke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How ſhin'd great <hi>Brittaines</hi> Lampes of late ſo cleere.</l>
               <l>Like Planets in their oppoſite aſpects,</l>
               <l>While Fathers rayes vpon his ſonne did peere,</l>
               <l>Reſuming ſplendor from his ſonnes reflects.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which glorious lights the world did late admire,</l>
               <l>Reciprocating betwixt the ſonne and ſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lending, and borrowing from each others light,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Phoebus</hi> throwes his rayes vpon the Moone,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4587:4"/>
               <l>Who repreſents his perſon in the night,</l>
               <l>Then yeilds her ſplendor when her courſe is done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To him, from whome ſhee borrow'd all her glore,</l>
               <l>Yet loſt no light by her, but gain'd the more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No more the great <hi>Apollo</hi> of this Ile</l>
               <l>Did looſe his light jmparting't to his ſonne,</l>
               <l>But gain'd a greater glorie all the while,</l>
               <l>While all redoubled, backe againe did runne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By Rayes of which reciprocating light,</l>
               <l>This Ile had alwaies day, and knew no night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Till death by interpoſing his darke hand,</l>
               <l>Did intercept thoſe beames, and holde them backe.</l>
               <l>Which ſpred a darke ecclipſe o're all this land,</l>
               <l>And chang'd all brightnes in Cimmerian blacke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By thoſe great Luminaries dire defects</l>
               <l>Portending moſt prodigious effects.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which God averte, and turne vpon our foes,</l>
               <l>Leaſt doubtleſſe this ſmall Ile at length become</l>
               <l>A boundleſſe continent of endleſſe woes,</l>
               <l>Reaping the juſte deſert of threatned dome.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Since Gods long ſuffring is at length out-runne,</l>
               <l>Whoſe judgements at his owne houſe are begunne,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God graunt our ſinnes procure no greater wrath</l>
               <l>Vppon our heads, but that wee once may turne</l>
               <l>To true repentance, by a lively fayth,</l>
               <l>And for our many ſinnes ſincerely mourne,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That God may in his mercie yet reſtore</l>
               <l>This darkened Iland to her former glore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And in the perſon of our tender Prince</l>
               <l>Renew thoſe lampes of diſcontinued light,</l>
               <l>Which haue beene droun'd in darkenes ever ſince</l>
               <l>That worthy Prince did bid the world goodnight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let never this ſmall Ile, while heavens remaine,</l>
               <l>Be dark'd with ſuch a dire eclipſe againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And though the braveſt branch be cut away,</l>
               <l>Yet ſeat the roote moſt ſtedfaſt in his place,</l>
               <l>To ſhine from <hi>Thames,</hi> and <hi>Trent,</hi> to <hi>Forth,</hi> and <hi>Tay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Eternall in his never ruin'd race.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4587:5"/>
               <l>From whence while earth indures may ſtill be one,</l>
               <l>To rule th'vnited Ile of <hi>Ath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So long as <hi>Tay,</hi> and <hi>Forth.</hi> and <hi>Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Thames.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Irrignates this Ile with chriſt all ſtreames.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ In Effigiem Principis.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SWeet ſenſleſſe ſtone that ſenſibly expreſſeth</l>
                  <l>A Princes perſon, in his mortall daies,</l>
                  <l>So artificiall, that each one confeſſeth,</l>
                  <l>The Caruers curious paines deſerueth praiſe;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That one ſmall ſparkle of <hi>Promethean</hi> fire,</l>
                  <l>Might make thy breathles body moue, and ſpire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That ſince th'immortall ſubſtance of his ſoule</l>
                  <l>Hath gain'd by death an everlaſting crowne,</l>
                  <l>And endles fame his vertues doth enro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de</l>
                  <l>In regiſters of never dark'd renowne;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His earthly parts which onely mortall bee,</l>
                  <l>May liue, and be immortaliz'de in thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That no part of ſo great a worth ſhould periſh,</l>
                  <l>But all be cloth'd with incorruption,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſoule, bones, vertues, heavens, art, fame do cheriſh</l>
                  <l>Againſt death, rottennes, and obliuion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>While either heavens, or arte, or fame ſhall liue,</l>
                  <l>No part of thoſe three parts ſhall not ſurviue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>While thou pure marble ſhalt poſſeſſe a place,</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the beſt of Engliſh Potentates</l>
                  <l>And with thy Princely preſence there ſhalt grace</l>
                  <l>The glorious crew of great Plantagenets.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where <hi>Henries, Edwards, Richards,</hi> ſtill ſurviue.</l>
                  <l>In Marble bodies as they ſeem'd aliue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why then thogh art can ſaue from earth's corruption,</l>
                  <l>The earths owne body, which is due to wormes:</l>
                  <l>Yet cannot ſo paint out the Soules perfection,</l>
                  <l>A greater taske then Painters art performes,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To braue oblivion with his memorie,</l>
                  <l>Concernes the ſacred art of Poetrie</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4587:5"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>And (ô would God) ſome <hi>Orpheus</hi> might ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe pow'rfull verſe did moue deafe Rockes to heare him,</l>
                  <l>While Beaſts, and Birds, and Stones, and Plants, and Trees,</l>
                  <l>And Nymphs, and Fawnes came thronging to be neare him.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let ſuch a one in golden lynes ſet forth</l>
                  <l>The jmage of his ſoules admired worth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If gazers ſwarme about his picture ſo,</l>
                  <l>To marke the ſweet reſemblance of his face:</l>
                  <l>What troupes, what worlds of men ſhould ſeeke to know</l>
                  <l>A mirror of his vertues, and his grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>While one amongſt the reſt that viewd his toombe</l>
                  <l>Diſtilling teares ſhould thus the reſt informe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heere lyes (but Ah how can hee lye ſo low?</l>
                  <l>Who living ſtill aſpired to be high.)</l>
                  <l>Yet heere he lies, (and doth his ſoule alſo?</l>
                  <l>No ſure it mounts jmmortall th'rough the ſkie)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heere lyes (why then where are his vertues gone?</l>
                  <l>And are thoſe too in toomb'de within this ſtone.)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Once more, heere lyes the body of a Prince,</l>
                  <l>Whome nature grace'd with ſuch divine perfection,</l>
                  <l>That all that e're were borne before, or ſince,</l>
                  <l>Did chooſe him for their chiefe by rare election.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Famous for learning, valor, wiſedome, worth:</l>
                  <l>Royall by vertue, beauty, bounty, birth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe childhood promiſ'de greater hope of praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Then ever Prince attained in his time,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe vertues made the fame of former dayes</l>
                  <l>Obſcured in the ſpringtide of his prime.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Till nature doubting ſo great grouth in ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>Should haue ſurpaſde even natures ſelfe at length.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Did cut him off by death, before his day,</l>
                  <l>Who even in dying, triumph'de o're that elfe,</l>
                  <l>Ah whither am I carri'd, heere jle ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt following him too farre, I looſe my ſelfe,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sith mortall pennes vnworthy are to write,</l>
                  <l>And too too baſe to treat a theame ſo great.</l>
                  <l>Sweet bones within your toombe, reſt ſtill in ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Till God rejoine you to the ſoule in glore.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4587:6"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>Epitaphium.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Two Kingdomes strone for Intreſt in one Prince,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heauens claim'd me from them both, and reft me hence;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Scotland <hi>my Cradle,</hi> England <hi>hath my Horſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Heauens my Soule, my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertues liue in verſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>I liv'd three Kingdomes hope, foes terror, Parents life,</l>
                  <l>I di'de their deareſt loſſe, their Ioy, their endles griefe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <head>To the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>GReat mightie Monarch of this mourning Ile,</l>
               <l>Whoſe griefe is ours, or ours is thine, or rather</l>
               <l>Both waile but one griefe, in a diff'rent ſtile,</l>
               <l>Thou mourning for a Sonne, we for a Father,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet all but one, who both was borne to bee</l>
               <l>A Sire to vs, but firſt a Sonne to thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our bliſſe, our bale is borrowed but from thine,</l>
               <l>For when thou weep'ſt, then we are drown'd in teares:</l>
               <l>And when ſome ſignes of joy beginne to ſhine</l>
               <l>In thy bright lookes, then mirth in vs appeares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not ſwerving once from thee in this, nor that,</l>
               <l>As if vpon thy brow we read our fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then if thou tenders (as no doubt thou does)</l>
               <l>Our weale (great King) lament his death no more</l>
               <l>Who cannot die, and then we cannot chooſe</l>
               <l>But doe the ſame, that thou haſt done before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Looke on thy living Sonne, and thou ſhalt ſee</l>
               <l>A liuely mirror both of him, and thee.</l>
               <l>Then in the <hi>Lethe</hi> of his chriſt all eyne.</l>
               <l>Intombe the thought of both our griefe, &amp; thine.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:4587:6"/>
            <head>To the Queenes Maieſtie.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHo ſeeks (great Queene) with words t'aſſwage thy woes,</l>
               <l>Would ſtop the Seas ſtrong tyde, with ſticks, and ſtroes.</l>
               <l>That over-flowing Ocean in thy breaſt</l>
               <l>Muſt haue free courſe, till high ſpring-tides be paſt,</l>
               <l>Yet when that planets pow're beginnes to wane,</l>
               <l>Solatious words may calme thoſe ſtormes againe.</l>
               <l>On this ſad ſubiect ſtill thy mind doth runne,</l>
               <l>And onelie this that thou haſt loſt a Sonne,</l>
               <l>And ſuch a Sonne as never Ladie loſt,</l>
               <l>Of whoſe match earth dare not be bold to boſt.</l>
               <l>Tis all moſt true, and therefore all the earth</l>
               <l>Was all vnworthy of ſo great a worth.</l>
               <l>More worthy farre to raigne with Saints in Heavens,</l>
               <l>Then ſit on earth to judge twixt oddes, and evens.</l>
               <l>Yet liv'd he long, although his life ſeem'd ſhort,</l>
               <l>That Ship ſailes moſt that ſooneſt gets her Port.</l>
               <l>He dies not ſoone that ſtill on death is muſing,</l>
               <l>Life's meaſur'd, not by time, but by times vſing.</l>
               <l>Meane men and Princes, all were borne to die,</l>
               <l>Death's the laſt line of mortall miſerie,</l>
               <l>The end of wandring, and the doore of reſt;</l>
               <l>Where he that ſooneſt comes, his lot is beſt.</l>
               <l>Then for a death ſo happy, to be ſorie,</l>
               <l>Is nothing, but to envie at his glorie.</l>
               <l>Though thou (great Queene) hath loſt what thou held deareſt,</l>
               <l>Yet two ſurviue, that to his worth come neareſt,</l>
               <l>Who now vnmatch'd, were once ſurmatch'd by him,</l>
               <l>But ſince no other to that height can clim,</l>
               <l>Sweet royall Impes grow ſtill more cleare and purer,</l>
               <l>Since he is gone, whoſe worth made yours obſcurer.</l>
               <l>Vnmatched now, but onelie each by other,</l>
               <l>An vnmatch'd Siſter to a matchleſſe Brother.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And after many yeares, and months, and daies,</l>
               <l>Liue both to cloſe your dying Parents eyes.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:4587:7"/>
            <head>To Prince <hi>CHARLES.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>ADmired <hi>Phoenix,</hi> ſpringing vp apace,</l>
               <l>From th'aſhes of another <hi>Phoenix</hi> bones,</l>
               <l>Which (too too courteous) yeelded thee his place,</l>
               <l>Leaſt earth were burden'd with two birds at once</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of that rare kind, which loues to liue alone,</l>
               <l>Whoſe onelie eſſence is to be but one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>T'was needfull (ſo heavens fatall verdict runnes)</l>
               <l>The firſt to die, the laſt ſpring from his embers.</l>
               <l>Heavens bounds (though boundleſſe) cannot hold two ſonnes,</l>
               <l>Nor earth containe two (more then) <hi>Alexanders,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And both ſo great, that yet the earth doth grone</l>
               <l>To beare ſo great a burden as the one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſince Heavens haue alloted thee to liue,</l>
               <l>Braue Prince, the mirror both of th'one, &amp; th'other,</l>
               <l>So Heavens I wiſh may to thy glorie giue</l>
               <l>Ioyn'd with thine owne, the vertues of thy Brother.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That thou a two-fold <hi>Phoenix</hi> may attaine,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Phoenix</hi> race of yeares on earth to raigne.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <head>To the Lady <hi>ELIZABETH.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>MIrrour for Ladies, in whoſe life contend</l>
            <l>Vertue, and beautie, which ſhould grace the moſt,</l>
            <l>Long may their ſtrife continue, without end,</l>
            <l>To grace thee ſtill, till life, and all be loſt.</l>
            <l>Which after many yeares, and daies, be done</l>
            <l>When fruitfull Rhine is cover'd with thy ſead,</l>
            <l>That from thy royall breaſt may ſpring ſome one,</l>
            <l>The living jmage of our Prince that's dead.</l>
            <l>Then thou may ſay, ſweet Youth, proceed in praiſe,</l>
            <l>Such was thy Princelie Vncle in his time,</l>
            <l>Such may thou be, but having longer daies,</l>
            <l>That all thy life may equall but his prime,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:4587:7"/>
            <l>Which if it doe, I boldlie dare divine,</l>
            <l>No others life ſhall ever equall thine.</l>
            <l>That both of you, when he thoſe words ſhall heere,</l>
            <l>May to his mem'rie ſacrifice a teere.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <head>To the Prince <hi>PALATINE.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe fame (braue Prince) of wonders in our Ile,</l>
               <l>Sprung from the Thames, aſtoniſhed the Rhine;</l>
               <l>That all Rhines dainties in thine eyes ſeem'd vile,</l>
               <l>To view thoſe wonders that were thought divine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which when thou croſt the raging Seas to ſee</l>
               <l>This Ile a litle Heaven did ſeeme to bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where three great lights all in a ſpheare did ſhine,</l>
               <l>From one great maine light borrowing their aſpects,</l>
               <l>No cloud came nigh to croſſe th'eclipticke line,</l>
               <l>They by his rayes, he bright by their reflects.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On whom ſhin'd backe the beames from all the three,</l>
               <l>Like Rivers paying tribute to the Sea.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But at thy comming came thoſe dire defects,</l>
               <l>That dim'd the greateſt light that grac'd our day,</l>
               <l>And thou to breed a ſecond ſadde eclipſe,</l>
               <l>Would lead the ſecond of the two away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet doe great Prince, for what thou mean'ſt to do,</l>
               <l>Is but t'jngraft another with the two,</l>
               <l>That three (though ſundred) yet may no leſſe ſhine,</l>
               <l>O're all the bounds betwixt the Thames and Rhine.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
